Calum Hand PhD.

calumhand201@gmail.com | (+44) 07765771639 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/calum-hand/ | Bristol, UK

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A highly motivated machine learning engineer with 3+ years experience in developing, and productionising end-to-end AutoML pipelines in drug discovery with a further 4+ years in chemistry based AI research. A subject matter expert across a range of technologies and their intersection with AI; always looking forwards to expand my knowledge to learn about new fields and help them succeed.

SKILLS

- o Technologies: Python, SQL, Metaflow, AWS, Git, Bash, SQLAlchemy, Poetry, OpenAI, Anaconda
- o Libraries: Pytest, Scikit-learn, Pytorch, Optuna, FastAPI, DuckDB, Pyarrow, Pandas, Numpy, Chromadb Numba, Cuda, MlFlow, RDKit
- o DevOps: Docker, CodeBuild, CodeDeploy, Github Actions

EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer

chemistry teams.

Remote, UK May 2022 - Current

 ${\it Glamorous~AI:An~X-CHEM~Subsidiary}$

May 2022 - Curren

Machine Learning Engineer Intern

Remote, UK Oct 2021 - April 2022

Glamorous AI: An X-CHEM Subsidiary

Worked on end-to-end training, deployment, and scaling of a range of AI models and other data-driven technologies to cloud environments for the "ArtemisAI" SaaS platform. Combined AI and domain experience to act as the intersection between AI and

• AI Research & Model Deployment:

- Deployed numerous AI models to production environments including: LM models (ChemBERTA), GNNs, NNs, and Random Forests (AWS, Docker, Python, Pytorch, Scikit-Learn)
- Implemented and trained state-of-the-art graph convolution networks for multi-input binding affinity prediction models (Pytorch, AWS Sagemaker, Docker, EC2, Python)
- Shortlisted and deployed several 3D CNN models for docking pose prediction to accelerate molecular docking simulations while minimising compute costs
- Integrated hyperparameter optimisation into production training pipelines, resulting in 10-15% model performance increase (Python, Docker, AWS, Optuna)

• Production Datastore:

- Independently planned and implemented the entire private data lakehouse to reduce computation times during AI training and inference by taking user input and transforming into persisted features for ML models (Python, DuckDB, SQL, Pyarrow, SQLAlchemy, S3, RDS)
- Designed the datastore to be a user friendly client library and tool, ensuring full adoption across research and engineering teams
- Reduced prediction pipeline run times by half

• LLM-Powered RAG User Guide Assistant:

- Developed a prototype RAG & LLM system allowing clients to query the platform's 100+ page documentation (FastAPI, ChromaDB, Docker, OpenAI)
- Managed end-to-end pipeline for updating and adding new documentation to RAG and updating existing documentation including data pre-processing, embedding generation, and fine-tuning query-response integration with LLM

• Domain Applicability Research:

- Led the research, development and optimisation of several unsupervised approaches to identify when the domain of the trained model doesn't match the domain of the prediction dataset (Python, Scikit-learn, Poetry, Pytest, Numpy, Optuna)
- Research was conducted on internal chemical datasets resulting in correctly identifying 66% of benchmark AI model prediction errors

• Docking Simulation Production Pipeline:

- Lead the design and productionization of a molecular docking simulation pipeline to pre-filter large molecular databases for high throughput drug candidate screenings (Python, Docker, Metaflow, Argo, Poetry, Pytest, SQLAlchemy)
- Completed pipeline could process hundreds of thousands molecules in under 2 hours while minimising costs through considered compute instance collection
- Designed P.O.C integrating with active learning screenings of large molecular datasets producing promising results

• Similarity Screening Production Pipeline:

- Designed and Implemented a large scale pipeline using EKS cluster for a molecular fingerprint similarity calculation achieving 2.5 billion similarity calculations in 10 minutes (Python, Docker, Metaflow, Pyarrow, Poetry, Pytest)

• Internal Tool Development:

- Visualisation of chemical library overlap
- Unified data retrieval pipelines from multiple public data sources
- Consolidated and a wide collection of metrics for molecular similarity
- (Python, Docker, github actions, Conda, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Dask, Numpy, Rdkit, Requests)

• Other Responsibilities:

- Routinely presenting to stakeholders and clients as a subvject matter expert
- Acting as scrum master in fortnightly agile development sprints
- Following TDD, striving for 90% test coverage in all projects worked on
- Instigating and organising a weekly meetup for the researchers to present problems and findings
- Maintaining AI prediction pipelines, internal data lakehouse, and associated APIs
- Conducted market analysis to identifying three further market areas for potential expansion with findings presented to stakeholders

IKEEP Collaborator Bath, UK

Co-Forest Ltd Feb 2021

- Worked as part of three person intrapreneurial knowledge exchange program between local business and PhD researchers
 Project involved creating a plan to establish sense of community within Co-forest public and industrial clients
- The outcomes of this collaboration included the identification of company goals in order to create content for specific customers and the drafting of relevant promotional materials.

Account Team Member London, UK

RIMES Technologies (Financial Data Management)

Aug 2017 - Aug 2018

- Was responsible for maintaining clients data feeds, including the investigation and analysis of any data discrepancies and errors raised in within RIMES in house coding language
- Rapidly promoted within six months to work with RIMES largest client, acting as subject matter expert and advising the client on the development of their new data feeds

Climbing Tower Staff & Counsellor

Virginia, USA

YMCA Camp Silver Beach

May 2015 - Aug 2015

- Worked as staff for the rock climbing tower and counsellor to cabin of 13 campers
- Expected to be autonomous in our day to day work caring for over 120 campers a week

EDUCATION

PhD in Chemical Engineering

Bath, UK

University of Bath

Oct 2019 - March 2023

Developed and applied machine learning techniques to reduce R&D costs in high throughput screenings

MRes Sustainable Chemical Technologies

Bath, UK

University of Bath

Sept 2018 - Sept 2019

Researched Active learning in material screenings, and novel vaccination preparations to mitigate cold chain risks

MRes Green Chemistry

London, UK

Imperial College London

Sept 2016 - Sept 2017

Developed novel synthetic routes to sustainable furan monomer units for organic based solar cells

BSc Chemistry with Medicinal Chemistry

St. Andrews, UK

University of St. Andrews

Sept 2012 - June 2016

Developed a novel synthetic route valorising ligning as a biorenewable source of aromatic carbon

PUBLICATIONS

- "Scalable Drug Property Prediction via Automated Machine Learning": J. Chem. Inf. Model.: Pending
- "Multi-Class Synthetic Accessibility Prediction" : J. Chem. Inf. Model. : Pending
- "Autonomous Exploration and Identification of High Performing Adsorbents using Active Learning" : *ChemRxiv* : 10.26434/ChemRxiv.14555706.V1
- "Bayesian Screening: Multi-test Bayesian Optimization Applied to in silico Material Screening": arXiv: 2009.05418
- "The synthesis of Hibbert ketone structures in technical lignins": Org. Biomol. Chem., 2016, 14, 10023 10030